<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><description>Behind the scenes at Arcfact, fiction and opinion about the future</description><title>Arcfinity</title><generator>Tumblr (3.0; @arcfinity)</generator><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/</link><item><title>We’ve been to see CODED MATTER(S) in Amsterdam</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sjef.nu/"&gt;Sjef van Gaalen&lt;/a&gt; explores codespace&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://media.tumblr.com/18b7968eb6c122c61261b992f7cbb7c9/tumblr_inline_mui3ihAjai1r6m0sx.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;small&gt;Coded Matter(s) is produced by FIBER (Amsterdam, NL)&lt;br/&gt; info@fiberfestival.nl / &lt;a href="http://www.fiber-space.nl"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.fiber-space.nl"&gt;www.fiber-space.nl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt; +31(0)641235624&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m in Amsterdam - more precisely, up on a balcony in the Flemish arts centre De Brakke Grond - for &lt;a href="http://www.codedmatters.nl/event/unfolding-space/"&gt;Coded Matter(s): Unfolding Space&lt;/a&gt;, the first in a series of events organised by the audiovisual network FIBER. We’re gathered here to explore how digital technologies are changing the fields of art, design and music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city isn&amp;#8217;t just bricks and mortar any more, you know: it&amp;#8217;s become infused with the network, code fusing with material hardware to form a new &amp;#8220;codespace&amp;#8221;. This is the kind of Smart City rhetoric you&amp;#8217;ll have undoubtedly encountered over the last few years - but don’t knock it. If nothing else, it’s been generating an extraordinary visual repertoire:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/cxdjfOkPu-E" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;Networks and the city merge: Timo Arnall&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;Immaterials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="281" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/71516975" width="500"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;3RD&lt;/em&gt; by DUS Architects and Monobanda&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="375" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/28258747" width="500"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;You can find out more about LAb[au]&amp;#8217;s practice in their monograph &lt;a href="http://lab-au.com/#/medias/2010_metadesign---labau/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;MetaDeSIGN&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introductory talk by Michiel de Lange is, well, introductory, and Els Vermang of LAb[au]is here to do little more than show and tell. Moco Raffael Ziegler of &lt;a href="http://www.elektropastete.de/"&gt;Elektropastete&lt;/a&gt; promises more. For a start, he’s rocking a bad-ass Spock Shirt. His snappy presentation shows the evolution of Elektropastete from the joking &amp;#8220;Verein zur Förderung Elektronischer Tanzmusik&amp;#8221; (Society for the Promotion of Electronic Dance Music) to a legit company doing award-winning work for high-profile agencies. It&amp;#8217;s basically another projects show and tell, but their work with projection mapping and drone swarm installations are well worth checking out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="281" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/40649165" width="500"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/cseTX_rW3uM" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.enist.org/v3/"&gt;Daniel Berio&lt;/a&gt; rounds off the evening. He created the Graffitizer, the only physical installation present at the event:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="375" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/43499784" width="500"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installation algorithmically generates vector shapes based on Berio’s sketching style, then projects these onto a paper screen while a plotter draws on the shape outlines. The machine can be left to auto-generate works which Daniel sees as just souvenirs of the installation; but he also has a GUI through which to tweak the variables and steer the form of the output, using it to generate other artworks, paintings, and laser-cut 3D collages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A wrap-up panel discussed the dread level of these new technologies, and explored questions of ownership around the codebase that enables and underpins these works. It ended the way these panels usually end &amp;#8212; with the hapless panellists having to explain what art is but a performance of Trinity by Oscar Sol and Iris Heitzinger, aka &lt;a href="http://electronicperformers.in/index.html"&gt;Electronic Performers&lt;/a&gt;, brought the evening to a rousing conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="281" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/69152711" width="500"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An IR cam captures the dancers&amp;#8217; movements, then uses the stage floor as a projection canvas upon which algorithmic augmentations of her movements are mapped, creating an exploration of sound, visuals and human movement through space that successfully delights and disturbs. If you have a chance to see this performance live anywhere I highly recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first Coded Matter(s) event in a series that FIBER are running alongside the annual FIBER Festival, and I&amp;#8217;d say overall it was a success. It sold out and the waiting list was long, so better get your tickets on time if you want to attend the next event on Sunday 10 November, the afternoon matinee &lt;a href="http://www.codedmatters.nl/event/sound-hackers/"&gt;Sound Hackers&lt;/a&gt;. An investigation of new expressions in sound and music, it features a great roster of interactive audio works and talks. See you there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/thesjef"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@thesjef&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.arcfinity.org/buy.php#previous-issues"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumit Paul-Choudhury loses his musical grip. Read &amp;#8220;Midnight at the Singularity Disco&amp;#8221; in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Afterparty Overdrive&lt;/em&gt; (Arc 1.3)&lt;/strong&gt;, out now. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/58639538540/were-improving-reality-with-honor-harger"&gt;Also on the blog: multimedia curator &lt;strong&gt;Honor Harger&lt;/strong&gt; talks to Simon Ings.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/63632894851</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/63632894851</guid><pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2013 10:01:00 +0100</pubDate><category>digital future</category><category>installation</category><category>art</category><category>music</category><category>urbanism</category><category>technology</category><category>quadcopter</category><category>internet of things</category><category>Amsterdam</category><category>FIBER</category><category>Coded Matters</category></item><item><title>We’re reading STARDUST by Nina Allan</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clowns, carnivals and halls of mirrors have been used in horror stories often enough, but rarely to such effect, says Liz Sourbut&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://media.tumblr.com/b826082656da2c5b531de740f79b163a/tumblr_inline_mucwyxvhlQ1r6m0sx.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;small&gt;PS Publishing, HB £11.99&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stardust: The Ruby Castle Stories&lt;/em&gt; is a collection of beautifully written stories, tenuously linked by largely fleeting mentions of the actress Ruby Castle, and by various themes of illusion, carnival, failure and loss. The stories are carefully-observed reflections on human nature, each with a macabre or horrific twist. The settings range from London to post-war Germany to a future Russia following a range of characters all of whom, in their own way, are chasing ghosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tone is often claustrophobic. In &amp;#8220;Laburnums&amp;#8221;, a frustrated poet who lives with her ageing mother is haunted by apparitions of her old school-friend Amma. But is Amma dead, or is she in fact a successful actress, who escaped the dreariness of everyday life? In &amp;#8220;The Gateway&amp;#8221;, a letter from an old friend sends Andrew chasing down memory lane to the day when he took young Claudia to the carnival and allowed her to enter the hall of mirrors alone&amp;#8230; Don’t look for closure in these stories. Most of them end on an ambiguous note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the opening story, &amp;#8220;B-Side&amp;#8221;, a young chess-player, obsessed by a fear of failure, is on his way home through a night-time park when he is accosted by two of the villainous characters from Ruby Castle’s movies. This fantastical and frightening incident offers the reader the first of several sparse glimpses into the actress’s life. As the protagonists of these stories grasp at fragments of the lives of others, so the reader will find, scattered through the stories, fragments of the life-story of Ruby Castle: just often enough to justify the book’s subtitle, never quite enough to satisfy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allan’s clean, spare prose lends her stories an immediacy and authenticity that is spine-chilling. Ambiguous ghosts surface repeatedly, haunting the narrators of almost every story. But are these the ghosts of the dead, or manifestations of people who are still living and only lost? Perhaps it is the narrators who are lost, and the ghosts who have moved on with their lives. Because in the end, for all their fantastic elements, what is truly spine-chilling about these stories is Allan’s pitiless exposure of human frailties, our capacity for self-delusion, betrayal and cowardice, and the degree of courage it takes for us to overcome our failings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also on the blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/63374527897/were-reading-neptunes-brood-by-charles-stross%22"&gt;Liz Sourbut tends &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;Neptune’s Brood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60920359296/were-reading-familiar-by-j-robert-lennon"&gt;M. John Harrison takes a psychotic break with J. Robert Lennon’s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Familiar&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/63544345504</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/63544345504</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 10:01:07 +0100</pubDate><category>short stories</category><category>horror</category><category>uncanny</category><category>collection</category><category>review</category><category>The Silver Wind</category><category>Spin</category></item><item><title>We’re reading NEPTUNE’S BROOD by Charles Stross</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A space opera about accountancy? It’s more than a gimmick, says Liz Sourbut.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://media.tumblr.com/d897f320d942c77e16d5e397a3231bef/tumblr_inline_muazhm60iK1r6m0sx.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;small&gt;Orbit, HB £16.99&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set in the same universe as Stross&amp;#8217;s earlier &lt;em&gt;Saturn&amp;#8217;s Children, Neptune’s Brood&lt;/em&gt; follows the outrageous adventures of an interstellar accountant. Or, more accurately, of a historian of accounting fraud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first space opera I recall reading that focuses on the interstellar banking system, and at its heart is a highly intricate long con. In a universe where no faster-than-light travel is possible (but hasn&amp;#8217;t been completely ruled out by the physics) Krina Alizond-114 is an academic accountant who specialises in studying variations on the &amp;#8220;FTL scam&amp;#8221;. Con artists try to persuade gullible marks that an FTL drive has in fact been invented but that something went wrong during the test flight and they just need a small advance to help them iron out the wrinkles in exchange for a share in untold future wealth. Krina and her distantly related sibling, Ana Graulle-90 have been following up clues in what looks to be the biggest FTL scam of all time. Now Ana has gone missing and as Krina goes in search of her she finds herself pursued by a murderous, non-conscious body-double. Her search takes her to the water-world of Shin-Tethys, first working her passage aboard a space-faring Church of the Fragile (the Fragile being flesh-and-bone humans, people like us) and later as prisoner-turned-crew-member of an &amp;#8220;independent customs inspection vessel&amp;#8221;, or privateer, captained by the bat-like Count (short for Accountant) Rudi. Once there, she is arrested, abducted, subjected to extreme forms of surgery and faces other challenges rarely encountered by academic accountants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neptune’s Brood&lt;/em&gt; drips with ideas, many of them thrown away in one-liners, and Stross’s vision of a high-tech post-human future in which the colonisation of the galaxy is being financed by what is effectively a pyramid selling scheme of deferred debt is hilariously plausible. The plot, though well constructed and satisfying, is almost incidental. What matters is how this complex, metahuman world unfolds. This is science fiction as Margaret Atwood would define it: filled with spaceships and giant talking squid, not to mention bats, mermaids and reanimated skeletons. It is baroque, clever, gruesome, riotous - quite frankly, it’s a delight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also on the blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/51548154258/were-reading-the-movement-of-stars-by-amy-brill"&gt;Liz Sourbut reviews Amy Brill’s &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;The Movement of Stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/48267649966/were-reading-the-bloodline-feud-by-charles-stross"&gt;Adrian Ellis braves Charles Stross’s &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;The Bloodline Feud.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/63374527897</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/63374527897</guid><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2013 15:43:23 +0100</pubDate></item><item><title>We're reading SHAMAN by Kim Stanley Robinson</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a&gt;Adam Roberts&lt;/a&gt; looks for the join between sf and historical fiction.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/3d637e4d32b8baed004192ef5cd534f3/tumblr_inline_mspvg5WfLg1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conversation -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;R: What are you reading? &lt;br/&gt; A: It’s the new Stan Robinson novel. It’s about Pleistocene men and women. &lt;br/&gt; R: What, like Tony Hart’s Morph?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- leads me to think there are people in the world who could do with being better educated about our paleolithic forebears. And this vivid, thoroughly researched and thoroughly absorbing novel could be the way. Were Tony Hart still alive, I feel sure he would agree with me. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; A little while ago, news of the subject of Kim Stanley Robinson’s new book &lt;a href="http://kimstanleyrobinson.info/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=172:coming-in-2013-ad-shaman&amp;amp;catid=35:ksr&amp;amp;Itemid=50"&gt;leaked onto the web&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;"I&amp;#8217;m finishing a novel set in the ice age, about the people who made the paintings in the Chauvet-Pont-d&amp;#8217;Arc Cave in southern France, about 32,000 years ago," he said. "I do a lot of snow camping in the Sierra, and I put my snow knowledge into it and tried to explain how we became who we are now.” &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;  &amp;#8221;It&amp;#8217;s only science and archaeology that allow us to write historical fiction with any accuracy,&amp;#8221; Robinson added. &amp;#8220;So it&amp;#8217;s kind of science fiction in a way.&amp;#8221;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robinson can call his novel what he likes, and I’ve never been one to force pigeonholing definitions on a book, but I have to say it really doesn’t read like SF. There are glancingly fantastic elements to it: it is narrated not by one of the characters, but by &amp;#8220;the third wind&amp;#8221;, a sort of supernatural force that comes to people &lt;em&gt;in extremis&lt;/em&gt; and helps them find the inner resources to push on through, something often needful in the world of this book. From time to time the p.o.v. shifts inside the head of a bear or wolverine, without altering very much. But mostly, though, &lt;em&gt;Shaman&lt;/em&gt; is given over to a detailed rendering of ice-age quotidiana. The ordinary day-to-day of a small tribe of early humans, living well-enough in the summer, struggling with the cold and ever-present starvation in the long winter. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The narrative of &lt;em&gt;Shaman&lt;/em&gt;, such as it is, concerns three things. One is young Loon being picked by the tribe’s Shaman, Thorn, as his successor, and having to learn all the lyrics to &amp;#8220;Ebeneezer Goode&amp;#8221;, sorry, I mean: learn all the shamanistic rites and stories. Two is Loon falling in love with and marrying a girl from a different tribe called Elga. It seems Shamans (Shamen?) aren’t supposed to marry, but Loon does so anyway. Three is a lengthy inset narrative set-piece: Elga and Loon are taken as slaves by a tribe of northerners. These people keep domesticated wolves and (because they hunt seal on the ice, amongst other things) aren’t starving all the time like our protagonists’ tribe—in other words, they are us, or more like us; and Robinson introduces them to play a variant of the game William Golding plays in &lt;em&gt;The Inheritors&lt;/em&gt;. When Thorn and a geezer called Click help Elga and Loon escape, there is a prolonged, tense chase across most of the length of prehistoric France, and we’re cheering for them to get away. The only niggle is, it’s too exciting; or, to be a little more precise, it’s exciting after the manner of the standard chase-and-flight thriller. It jars a little, when read against the background of the rest of the novel, because in &lt;em&gt;Shaman&lt;/em&gt; as a whole the excitement is of a completely different, and much rarer kind. Very little happens in this exteriorised, frantic, adrenalin-rushy way; and it is enormously to Robinson’s credit that, nonetheless, he manages to write this in such a way that we, as readers, are so wholly drawn in to the ordinary struggles of life. He pays us the compliment, in fact, of assuming that we will be interested in the ordinary goings-on of ordinary people. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; In the paleolithic, these goings-on mostly concerned getting food. Other goings-on included: dealing with the elements; encountering bears and wolverines and so on that might eat you; keeping a respectful distance from the Old Folk - Neanderthals - would were also liable to kill you; telling and listening to stories. But the overwhelming sense of paleolithic life one gets from reading this novel is what it is like subsisting on little or no food for long stretches. What it feels like when your belly button is a fingers-width away from your spine. How Elga’s substantial breasts simply melt away from the withering lack of calories. One thing the novel does rather brilliantly is have you empathising with an aesthetic of female beauty that inspired the maker of the celebrated Venus of Willendorf figurine. There are many, often beautiful descriptions of landscape, weather and animals. People get on with the business of life. Sometimes they go into caves and paint animals and people on the walls. All this is related to the reader in Robinson’s leisurely, precise, unshowy but vivid prose. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; There is less actual shamanistic stuff than I thought there was going to be: some songs and rituals, the occasional encounter with a ghost, and no spirit-flights into the northern lights or shape-changing-into-a-bear-and-back. But then again Robinson’s tenor has always been Realist. That might look like an odd thing to say about him, given that his vehicle over the years has mostly been fantastic—science fictional. But it’s so common a textual strategy in our genre as to be, really, the norm: a fantastical premise elaborated via careful research, respectful attention to the laws of science, and a style and form that owe much more to Zola than Borges: the accumulation of a great many precisely observed details, prose that aims to be as transparent and neutral as possible, the whole aesthetic game of verisimilitude. I’ve never been entirely sure why so many SF writers should want to match non-realist subjects with realist textual strategies. Perhaps where one improbability - the SFnal premise - is swallowable, adding a non-probable style is an unlikelihood too far. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; At any rate, Robinson’s scrupulous attention to detail and plausibility pays dividends. Bottom line: you believe it. Indeed, I found myself wondering just how far Robinson went by way of practical research. When Loon eats a bear penis, and the narrator says &amp;#8220;the penis was chewy and tasted like kidneys&amp;#8221;, is this a canny guess by KSR, or did he pop down to his local deli and order himself a raw bear penis just to… you know? Is there a writerly equivalent to Method Acting? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Mind you, verisimilitude is more than just a matter of what flints people used to scrape animal hides with. It has a larger, we could say ideological component to it as well. And, slaver-Northmen aside, &lt;em&gt;everybody in the book is nice&lt;/em&gt;. This is a point worth dilating upon, since it’s part of Robinson’s writerly &lt;em&gt;modus operandi&lt;/em&gt;, and may have something to do with his Marmite reputation amongst readers. (To be clear: I love KSR with a genuine passion, but I know folk who do not.) Loon, through whom most of this story is filtered, is an immensely likeable individual: resourceful, charismatic, brave and enduring. But then, everybody in his tribe is nice. One of the men admits to forcing sex on his wife whether she’s in the mood or not, and all the other men are immediately and vocally horrified with him. Women are to be respected, not objectified! It’s a commendable sentiment, although I wonder how pre-historically accurate it is. KSR’s position seems to be: the default setting of humankind is basically nice. He believes that, statistical outliers aside, we all basically want to get along, to not hurt other people, to live in balance. His last novel, the marvellous &lt;em&gt;2312&lt;/em&gt;, is like this too: its human characters are various and multitudinous, and some have &amp;#8220;attitude&amp;#8221;, but all are pretty nice, deep down, and that niceness - the capacity for collective work towards a common goal, the tendency not to oppress or exploit - is common to almost all the characters Robinson has written. His creations almost always lack inner cruelty, or mere unmotivated spitefulness, which may be a good thing. I’m not saying he’s wrong about human nature, either; although it is more my wish than my belief. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Another question is how timely, or otherwise, a book like this is. Caveman/woman fiction has its &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;en vogue&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; periods, and its periods when it falls from fashion. Conceivably it is coming back into fashion—Stephen Baxter&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;Northland Trilogy&lt;/em&gt; (or, strictly, the first volume, &lt;em&gt;Stone Spring&lt;/em&gt;, 2010) was well received, and &lt;em&gt;The Croods&lt;/em&gt; did pretty well at this year’s box office. Perhaps &lt;em&gt;Shaman&lt;/em&gt; will ride a new wave of interest in the period. I’m not so sure, though. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The last time we saw this, I’d say, was the 70s/80s, a period I’m old enough, being older than many paleolithic individuals managed (Hah! IN YOUR FACE!) to remember pretty well. Jean M. Auel’s &lt;em&gt;Clan of the Cave Bear&lt;/em&gt; (1980; there were many sequels) is doubtless less cheesy in actuality than it is in my memory of reading it as a teen; yet that memory is positively gorgozolaesque, not helped by the thought of Daryl Hannah in animal skins with her carefully coiffured, just-tangled-enough bottle-blond hair, like an LA model on a shoot. Auel’s series was huge for a while, of course, and it spoke to a set of distinctively 80s concerns, partly to do with nascent environmentalism, and the sense that civilisation had alienated us from &amp;#8220;authentic&amp;#8221; living. It was around this time that Walter L. Voegtlin’s &amp;#8220;Paleolithic diet&amp;#8221; was first promulgated, the core assumption of which is that a return to the eating habits of the sorts of people Robinson writes about is the royal road to health and fitness. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Before that we had the Flintstones and its analogues (all those frozen-caveman-awakens-in-the-modern-world yarns, from &lt;em&gt;Stig of the Dump&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Californian Man&lt;/em&gt;), in which comedy is generated by the ironic gap between stone age primitivism and modern day technological convenience -although I’ve never been sure whether the point here is to intimate that primitivism is buried just below the surface of modern civilised manners, or on the contrary to flatten history and insist that people &amp;#8220;back then&amp;#8221; were basically exactly the same as white US suburbanites, &lt;em&gt;no matter how far back we go&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Robinson’s project is not like that, I think; and though I finished &lt;em&gt;Shaman&lt;/em&gt; as full of respect for his prodigious gifts as a novelist and imaginer as ever, I did not, quite, fall in love with the novel the way I have with some of his earlier books. In part it may be that I found less by way of genealogical connection between those days and these. It made me glad I have no problem sourcing food in the winter; and that I have a nice brick structure to live in. Otherwise I wondered about its point of connection with modern life. But then, I’ve never eaten a raw bear penis. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also on the blog: &lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/52289912683/were-mourning-the-loss-of-jack-vance"&gt;Adam Roberts says goodbye to Jack Vance.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.arcfinity.org/buy.php"&gt;Read Kim Stanley Robinson in Arc 1.4, out now.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/61099398905</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/61099398905</guid><pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2013 10:00:40 +0100</pubDate><category>book</category><category>review</category><category>prehistory</category><category>Historical Novel</category></item><item><title>We’re reading up on TRANSHUMANISM</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We gave &lt;a href="http://www.paulgrahamraven.com/"&gt;Paul Graham Raven&lt;/a&gt; two books we knew he would want to hurl across the room, in the hope he would hurl them &lt;em&gt;into each other&lt;/em&gt;, in the manner of the Large Hadron Collider at CERN. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We were not disappointed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/6694e3992eff165485e4973f1863c910/tumblr_inline_msq38shrNs1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/c44a52d09eb9b4540c6b6e5dd1d7b97b/tumblr_inline_msq300Xyrr1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;small&gt;Transhumanism: A Grimoire of Alchemical Agendas&lt;br/&gt; Scott D de Hart &amp;amp; Joseph P Farrell&lt;br/&gt; Feral House, PPB £14.99&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;small&gt;The Transhumanist Reader: Classical and Contemporary Essays on the Science, Technology, and Philosophy of the Human Future&lt;br/&gt; edited by Max More &amp;amp; Natasha Vita-More&lt;br/&gt; John Wiley &amp;amp; Sons, PPB £19.99&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s been around a while, of course. Instantiated back in the pioneer era of the intertubes, transhumanism has been both well known to and somewhat intersectional with geek/tech, SilVal and sci-fi circles for a couple of decades. It’s a word that denotes either a proud and optimistic allegiance to a certain sort of transcendent futurity, or a complex of willfully unexamined scientisms and technofetishes, depending on who uses it and who is being described; a badge of membership or a badge of othering, in other words, like most subcultural identifiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even as the gap grows between transhumanist philosophical doctrine and what we might call Retweet Transhumanism, the former is doing its best to get its feet under the intellectual table. The latter can be all too easily mistaken for a kind of scientism cosplay, remarkably analogous to the more dogmatic sections of science fiction fandom (wherein unexamined catechisms are reiterated enthusiastically on the internet, with an exponential decline in signal-to-noise ratio), but this is nothing unusual. While weekend punks haunted the King’s Road charging tourists for mohawk photo opportunities, the ethos that powered punk was busily revolutionising art and identity politics, working on unseen in the unglamorous interstices; the most obvious and attention-grabbing elements of any subculture are inevitably the least interesting in the long run. But it&amp;#8217;s cropping up in social science journals, at conferences and in broadsheet science articles, because the technological underpinnings of transhumanism look a little less hypothetical than they did even five years ago. IVF babies with genes from three different parents? Increasingly subtle and ubiquitous sports doping? These are transhumanist issues, my friend!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As risible as Retweet Transhumanism can appear, the philosophy’s most &lt;!-- more --&gt;fervent opponents don’t always come across as balanced and rational questers after truth, either. &lt;em&gt;Transhumanism: a Grimoire of Alchemical Agendas&lt;/em&gt; is an interesting case in point, choosing as it does to tackle the real and profound questions of human identity and technoscientific ethics raised by transhumanist thought by grandiosely reframing it as the immanent, inevitable and pre-ordained end-game of a pre-Abrahamic (and possibly proto-global) tradition of transcendental alchemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, it’s utterly batshit, make no mistake - but in a manner for which I still have a residual affection, having a long pre-internet history of contact with the classic texts of occultism, conspiracy theory and cryptorevisionist speculation. You learn to recognise the style after a while: the grand conjectures swept past quickly, the confirmatory minutia dwelt upon for as long as they can withstand it, the call-backs to established grand (counter)narratives, the creative interpretations of the texts of ancient religions which put the conceptual acrobatics of po-mo lit-crit to shame. The occult’s appeal is captured in its name, of course: if we knew more about these ancient mysteries, they would lose their ability to enthrall. But they remain a hybrid combination of Rorschach blot and join-the-dots puzzle that can be overlaid arbitrarily on any other period of history or field of human endeavour, seeming to reveal the hidden pattern beneath the surface. De Hart and Farrell&amp;#8217;s edifice of flim-flam and standard riffs - the Rockefellers! Biblical apocrypha! secret societies! - is like some bizarre fusion of stoner &lt;em&gt;X-Files&lt;/em&gt; fandom, an online webinar devoted to spurious theological rhetoric, and Erik von Däniken enduring a particularly heroic amphetamine comedown among the stacks of the Bodleian Library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its coherence is little helped by what could be charitably described as a hands-off approach to editing and proofing, but convolution and self-referentiality is de Hart and Farrell&amp;#8217;s modus operandi - as is quoting huge chunks of their earlier books verbatim, said chunks themselves replete with badly formatted quotes and citations, resulting in a text where you’re never quite sure which parenthetical layer of argument you’re currently caught in, like playing an elaborate LARP in a hotel by Escher where the numbers in the lifts never light up. So often do de Hart and Farrell hedge their conclusions with reminders that &lt;em&gt;it’s all just pure speculation, of course!&lt;/em&gt; that one starts to suspect the lady of protesting too much; one wonders whether books of this ilk come out like they do because their authors know what their market wants and that they can score a cheque if they crank out some more (or, in this case, some More?), or because they really believe what they’re saying. (I’m never sure which answer would worry me the most.) Either way, there’s not much here that would-be defenders of transhumanism need worry themselves over, beyond eye-strain and the urge to correct typos. But there’s a salutary lesson here for would-be constructors of new metanarratives: the more gaps, conjecture and ambiguity you leave in, the more you appeal to their biases and intuitions, the more willingly the credulous will do the hard work of convincing themselves that you’re right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to the surest sign of transhumanism’s philosophical arrival: &lt;em&gt;The Transhumanist Reader&lt;/em&gt;. There comes a time in every young philosophy’s life when it must stand up and make its own way in the marketplace of ideas, and if you wanna do that without being subsumed, then you need an identifiable canon, a defensible beach-head from which to commence the big push inland. The responsibility and privilege of defining that canon falls to Dr Max More and Dr Natasha Vita-More, whose chosen names never fail to remind me of &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0GvVbIhKh-M"&gt;one of the earliest Simpsons episodes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can’t fault niche scholars for making every effort to amplify their visibility, I suppose; it’s a sharkpool out there, and those consulting gigs and invitations-to-speak won’t land themselves. But (Vita-)More&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;’s appellational alterations fit their field, which is likewise long on blithe confidence and boardroom bravado – a necessity, perhaps, given how much of the heavy lifting gets done with technoscientific speculation. Don’t take transhumanists for fools or easy targets, though; it&amp;#8217;s very much a scene populated by highly educated people who&amp;#8217;re smart enough to think highly of their own intelligence, and to use it to their best advantage. Indeed, I suspect the academy’s failure to take it more seriously has been to transhumanism’s advantage thus far, leaving it to (cherry)pick its most public battles from a succession of straw men and kneejerk reactions provided by the sort of marginal cranks who knew enough about it to have formed an opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Dr More studied at philosophy at Oxford; one wonders idly if he ever encountered de Hart and Farrell. Do philosophers and theologians still hang out? Or do they just glare sullenly at one another from opposite sides of the room at faculty mixers?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That may sound a little snooty, but it’s notable how much of the content of &lt;em&gt;The Transhumanist Reader&lt;/em&gt; is pretty old, at least by the standards of the internet. (I mean, c&amp;#8217;mon – mid-Nineties? That&amp;#8217;s literally last century!) One could argue, as (Vita-)More&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; do, that a canon should attempt to present the development of the ideas in their historical context - but for a philosophy entirely predicated on the importance and (literal) vitality of cutting-edge science and technological change, you’d perhaps be forgiven for thinking that there’d be more recent works that made better (or at least more robust) defences of the principles in light of recent research developments. Unless, that is, you&amp;#8217;ve spent any time reading actual contemporary research literature around cognition, behavioural psychology, neuroscience, linguistics and so forth, in which case you&amp;#8217;ll recognise the close relationship transhumanism shares with corporate futurism and other diegetic narratives of technoscience; given their long affinity with the occult, I&amp;#8217;m surprised de Hart and Farrell didn&amp;#8217;t recognise the sympathetic magics of a cargo cult when they encountered them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s lots of material here culled from the early Extropian mailing lists and website(s), and from their in-house journal, &lt;em&gt;Extropy&lt;/em&gt;; some of these have undergone iterative revision since their original appearance, but this particular canon is still very much Old Testament, with a few of the more recent Gospels and a mild heresy or two thrown in. Also of interest is just how many of those articles and essays from Extropian history are copyrighted to Dr More himself, as opposed to their authors, &lt;em&gt;Extropy&lt;/em&gt; or anyone else; say what you like, but here’s a guy who knows how to keep control of a canon once it’s been defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what does the canon say? There’s a gamut of side-chapels and flying buttresses - the more marginal technological speculations of transhumanist discourse that push the same buttons as aspirational sci-fi, such as emergent super-human AI, nanotechnological superabundance etc etc - but the foundational pillar of transhumanism is the axiom that &lt;em&gt;the extension and augmentation of human life and abilities through technological means is both achievable and desirable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part of that axiom - the bit about achievability - is hard to refute in principle, though much easier once you start wrestling specific claims; this may be why Dr More points out early on that transhumanism is not in the business of making predictions as to when a transhuman technology might become viable (p15), but is purely focussed on exploring the ramifications of the possibilities which are supposedly implicit in the technological development curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(One might further note that Dr More is emphatically not a Singularitarian, though there is a section in the &lt;em&gt;Reader&lt;/em&gt; devoted to the Singularity, that ironically singular catch-all for an ill-defined plurality of techno-eschatologies.; the Singularity section is right near the back, and features more blithe and sweeping claims about timeframes for transhumanist technologies than any other section of the book. Not all rhetoric is verbal; history demonstrates that a canon-builder would be wise to nurture a few heresies that can be thrown under the bus when the critics show up.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given how profoundly medicine and other technologies have transformed human health and lifestyles even in just the last few decades, an extrapolatory claim that more powerful augmentations and longer lifespans are in the pipeline is uncontroversial, perhaps even incontrovertible. The more biopolitically-focussed essays in the &lt;em&gt;Reader&lt;/em&gt; all concede this point in one conditional way or another; even the interview with Dr Michael H Shapiro – who harbours a sincere concern about the socioeconomic impact of unevenly distributed augmentation and longevity, and hence provides much of what little substantive criticism can be found in this book – points out that outright bans on seductive technologies like advanced prostheses, tailored performance-enhancing chemicals and in-utero genetic modification will merely push them out into the black-market badlands where regulation cannot reach (pp281-288; according to the footnotes, this piece “is not an exact transcription of the [original] interview&amp;#8221;). As those 3-way-DNA headlines attest, we will inevitably find desirable uses for these technologies, and after the desires will come the ethical justifications. The question that remains is how to deal with these desires as they become fulfillable; the transhumanist answer is, by and large, “full speed ahead, and damn the torpedoes&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to the heart of the matter: it is the desirability – the inherent moral goodness – of technological augmentation that is the axiomatic horn to watch most carefully, because it’s here that the generous extrapolations of the horn of achievability get weaponised. Once you’ve conceded that, OK, maybe we &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; use technology to make some substantial functional changes to what it means to be human, maybe we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; keep pushing our lifespan envelope, you’re wide open to the H+ suckerpunch: if we can, why should we not? Indeed, if we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt;, then surely we &lt;em&gt;must!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This basic argument comes in a variety of flavours, strengths and sophistications, depending on the context and who is wielding it. There are plenty of poorly disguised arguments from the position of individual liberty (“I want to, so I should be able to, and if you stop me you hate freedom&amp;#8221;) floating about in here, but the weakness and spoiled-teenager petulance of that particular tack (and others) is taken on by Patrick D Hopkins (pp345-352); it’s when we move out into the moral minefield that the swashbuckling sophistry begins in earnest. Dubious imperatives abound: for instance, if we can agree that most people would prefer to live longer, then living longer is surely a general human good, and thus withholding the technology to extend life further would then be equivalent to letting someone die before their time, right? The most ludicrous extension of this shaky argument is provided by Dr Aubrey de Grey, who had heretofore seemed to me to be one of the more reasonable minds on the transhumanist ticket. &lt;em&gt;Au contraire:&lt;/em&gt; in de Grey’s view, the argument above extends so far that even to advise caution and regulation in the development and deployment of lifespan extension is, by way of potentially excluding all the oldest folk currently alive from living yet longer, morally equivalent to defending ethnic cleansing based on age (p217).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(One wonders if perhaps certain negative impacts of human senescence may manifest sooner and more subtly than others.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a great deal of this spurious moral calculus to be found in transhumanist arguments: the trick is to secure an admission of the clear and immediate benefits to an individual promised by technology X or intervention Y, and then to triumphantly conclude that to refuse such a thing to anyone who might benefit from it would thus be immoral. The frequency of this particular flourish suggests that it doesn’t seem stupid to those who use it, even if it seems ridiculous to me. There is a good reason for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr More and allies are keen to uphold the party line: transhumanism is not a religion, nor is it an ideology. It is frequently accused of being both; Dale Carrico once incisively tweeted that “Transhumanism wants to be Scientology when it grows up&amp;#8221;, for instance, and it&amp;#8217;s an illuminating comparison. Again, (Vita-)More&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;have kept some handy heresies around against someone taking this line more strongly; witness Giulio Prisco, who cheerfully admits that he doesn’t believe in god or think that transhumanism is a religion, but that he thinks he should maybe make a “religion-like UI&amp;#8221; for transhumanism, so as to spread the Good Word to those who aren&amp;#8217;t switched on by photoshopped design fictions of happy supercyberpersons or exponential graphs lacking a scalar legend. If nothing else, you’ve got to admire his chutzpah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my money, transhumanism isn’t a religion in the same way that mindfulness isn’t Buddhism. But religions and philosophies are closely related types of metanarrative (as a character in Ken MacLeod’s &lt;em&gt;Intrusion&lt;/em&gt; puts it, “religion is philosophy for beginners&amp;#8221;), and as Bruno Latour argues so eloquently in &lt;em&gt;The Modern Cult of the Factish Gods&lt;/em&gt;, there is little or no functional difference between the metanarratives of religion and the secular metanarratives of science, progress and so forth. By enshrining a retconned iteration of Enlightenment values at the heart of their enterprise, transhumanists commit the irrationality of making a deity of rationality; whether your confidence is placed in a sky-fairy like Yahweh or an idea like Progress, Free Markets&lt;sup&gt;™&lt;/sup&gt; or Perpetual Growth, it is still a faith, a socially constructed truth-narrative. If that comparison troubles you, then there’s a question you’ve left unasked of yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transhumanism may not be ideological in and of itself, but by Dr More’s own admission, its adherents tend to skew very strongly toward identifying with libertarian politics by comparison with the general population (p13); one might note also the predominance of male WASPs in the TOC of the &lt;em&gt;Reader&lt;/em&gt;, a correlation that pops up elsewhere with reliable frequency. It’s in this context that the logics which look so flawed to me must seem utterly solid to those using them: if transhumanism is a piece of philosophical software, then it requires an up-to-date build of the fedora-wearing libertarian OS on which to run, assuming you want all advertised functionalities to be fully supported. With these dependencies met, everything starts to make more sense, and the doctrines of transhumanism flow freely along the impregnable slipways of established Randian reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those flawed suckers still unwilling to let objectivism save us from our own irrational and non-market-compliant altruisms, though, there’s a lingering doubt, even when the inevitability of the achievability of augmentation seems clear. There’s something missing from this book, and from transhumanism in general. Let’s go back to that core axiom, that enhancement and life extension is both achievable and desirable; now assume, for a moment, that you accept the transhumanist definition of desirability (whose clarity is inversely proportional to the number of words expended in dancing around it), and observe where that desire is located, and from which vantage it is assessed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The desirability and goodness of augmentation and life extension is always and explicitly located in the individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is absent from this book, and from the transhumanism it defines, is community, society. Oh, there’s talk of the transhuman community, of course (when a transhumanist says “we&amp;#8221;, they don&amp;#8217;t mean &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; unless you&amp;#8217;re also a card-carrier), and society gets a few passing mentions, albeit usually as the source of restrictive regulatory practices and unjust laws impinging on the sovereignty of the individual. But transhumanist doctrine itself does not necessarily extend beyond the body of the transhumanist; so long as the transhumanist is permitted their transhumanity, then the rest of the world can go whistle. This is the shell-game of morphological freedom, wherein the transhumanist graciously concedes that they have no right to tell you what to do with your physicality or mind, just so long as you can’t stop them doing what they want to themselves. You look after yourself, I’ll look after me; what could be fairer than that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world less structurally unfair than the one I currently find myself inhabiting, that principle might do just fine. But what it lacks, what transhumanism lacks, and what the Californian ideology which underpins transhumanism lacks, is any sense of responsibility for the consequences of your actions &lt;em&gt;upon others&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s not even that the questions are so new or hard to formulate; the social sciences are grappling hard with them as we speak, in an attempt to resolve the paradox of a world where transhumanists can talk blithely about “improving&amp;#8221; and “extending&amp;#8221; human capacities without addressing the questions of where the implied baseline is and who gets to police it, and where politicians can talk about market-enabled choice and “diverse healthcare outcomes&amp;#8221; while framing disability or long-term illness as one of many ways that the feckless supposedly sponge off of the state. It&amp;#8217;s as a part of this globally diffuse paradigm of me-first-why-not privilege that transhumanism starts to look less like an oddball cybercultural anomaly and more like yet another proxy front for oligarchy-as-usual. As James Bridle says, “technology is the reification and instrumentalisation of human desires&amp;#8221;; nowhere is that more plain to see than transhumanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spectres of people-other-than-oneself (so unknowable! so unpredictable! so prone to disapprove of your goals and resent your success!) haunt the biopolitical pieces in the Reader to a greater or lesser degree, but are largely banished from the rest of the book, much of which takes on theoretical questions (plasticity of identity, substrate-independence of minds, etc) far removed from the more immediate and testable socioeconomic issues implicit in the core transhumanist project. Concerns about a Gibsonian roll-out of longevity, wherein the augmentation would be unevenly distributed, are breezily handwaved away; other than the aforementioned Shapiro interview, the strongest engagement with it comes from Ronald Bailey, former climate change sceptic and science editor of &lt;em&gt;Reason&lt;/em&gt;, who basically says that uneven distribution would totally be a problem &lt;em&gt;if it happened&lt;/em&gt;, right? But it’s OK because we have systems in place to make sure things are fairly distributed (they’re not named explicitly, but I strongly suspect he means “markets&amp;#8221;) and it’ll all get real cheap real fast so everyone will be fine, yeah? And anyway, if you’re worried about uneven distribution, telling us to slow down is only going to slow down the distribution! So basically, yeah, you’re selfishly telling a whole planet full of people that &lt;em&gt;they’re&lt;/em&gt; not allowed to live longer because &lt;em&gt;you’re&lt;/em&gt; jealous of their money, which is typical leftist hypocrisy, because you&amp;#8217;re refusing to tolerate the free choices of others. Or, in Mr Bailey&amp;#8217;s own words, “egalitarian opponents of enhancement want to make sure that the rich and the poor remain equally diseased, disabled and dead&amp;#8221; (p337) – implying an extant cross-demographic equality in “healthcare outcomes&amp;#8221; for which I&amp;#8217;d love to see some solid evidence, particularly from Mr Bailey&amp;#8217;s own nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Of course, the time-worn utopian narrative of supply-side humanitarianism and economics as delivered by Bailey and many others, not all of them transhumanists, bears no relation to the functioning of actual markets and distributions as observed in the real world&amp;#8230; but that&amp;#8217;s because our markets just aren&amp;#8217;t free enough to match the theory yet!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel we can usefully return to Dr de Grey&amp;#8217;s moral-escalation argument above, however, in order to put this matter to rest. To recap: it is transhumanist doctrine that to wilfully stymie the development and deployment of technologies or medicines that could extend, augment or otherwise improve human life is morally equivalent to allowing or defending the deliberate infliction of illness, senescence and ultimately death on those whose access you restrict; further, if a technology exists which could extend, augment or otherwise improve human life, it should be developed and made as widely available as possible without further delay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I have good news: it turns out that technologies which extend, augment or otherwise improve human life are already here! You may have heard of some of them: clean water; urban sanitation; smokeless cooking facilities; free access to healthcare; a guaranteed minimum income; a good, free education. There are more – and you’d be surprised how many of them have been around in one form or another for decades, even centuries! But they’re unevenly distributed at the moment, so the first agenda item for all transhumanists should be looking for ways to get these technologies to everyone on the planet as soon as possible&amp;#8230; because if you don’t, &lt;em&gt;by your own logic&lt;/em&gt;, you are wilfully and consciously permitting millions if not billions of people to suffer totally avoidable misery, poverty, illness and death. Better still, you can start close to home; after all, what better test-case could there be for the even distribution of longevity improvement than &lt;a href="http://www.nationaljournal.com/domesticpolicy/life-expectancy-in-some-u-s-counties-is-no-better-than-in-the-third-world-20130710"&gt;the ~17 year lifespan differential between the wealthy and the poor in the United States itself?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*tumbleweed*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah, well. One way or another, transhumanism – or at least the ethical dilemmas around which transhumanism accretes – is here to stay for the foreseeable; perhaps it’ll evolve (dare I say &lt;em&gt;improve itself?)&lt;/em&gt; into something a little less venal as a wider range of people encounter the idea; perhaps it won’t. Perhaps my own baseline monkeydom and pinko-mutualist biases preemptively ensure I can’t grok the crystalline logics of transhumanism, leading me to see selfishness where there is only enlightened self-interest. Perhaps Dr More is right, and the precautionary principle really &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an unethical impediment to progress; why shouldn’t he be allowed to advance knowledge with new research, just in case someone or something might get hurt in the process? Why, you might as well shoot humanity in its collective foot! And if something does go awry, well, there are laws and frameworks for compensation and restitution, aren’t there? He&amp;#8217;s trying to secure a greater, brighter destiny for the race; punishing him for mistakes he might never make hardly seems fair, now, does it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps not - but even so, that’s an attitude I’d find alarmingly cavalier if I were in the market for having my head cryogenically frozen, say, and it were held by &lt;a href="http://www.alcor.org/AboutAlcor/meetalcorstaff.html#max"&gt;the CEO of the biggest company offering such a service&lt;/a&gt;. Hell, I wouldn&amp;#8217;t buy a used car from someone who&amp;#8217;d written that essay, let alone a promise of immortality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I can&amp;#8217;t afford cryogenics, and I still remain to be convinced that my life is somehow lessened by its finitude, and thus my Deathist cynicism destines me to expire before I even begin the epic journey of personal fulfilment which my transhuman life might be. What transhumanism can never seem to parse is that I can totally live with that&amp;#8230; and, furthermore, that most of the rest of the world doesn&amp;#8217;t even have the luxury of the choice of whether they live with it or not. Perhaps unsurprisingly, such positions are anathema to a philosophy whose central question could be rephrased as “what can you give the man who already has everything?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PaulGrahamRaven"&gt;@paulgrahamraven&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also on the blog: &lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/53840905866/weve-been-to-the-global-future-2045-international"&gt;David Varela witnesses strange goings-on at the Global Future 2045 International Congress.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.arcfinity.org/buy.php#previous-issues"&gt;Read Paul Graham Raven in our inaugural issue, on sale now.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/61010620946</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/61010620946</guid><pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2013 10:01:47 +0100</pubDate><category>book</category><category>review</category><category>extropian</category><category>transhumanism</category><category>frozen heads</category><category>technology</category><category>fetishism</category><category>philosophy</category></item><item><title>We’re reading FAMILIAR by J Robert Lennon</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://ambientehotel.wordpress.com/"&gt;M John Harrison&lt;/a&gt; finds himself on a road to nowhere.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/77b25a273fbfc8544fe655be1dab5b04/tumblr_inline_mspoozjXjn1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;small&gt;Serpent&amp;#8217;s Tail, PPB £11.99&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elisa Brown is a lab technician, married to Derek, whose speciality is “maritime law as it applied to the Great Lakes&amp;#8221;. It’s a stultified, low-key relationship. It’s familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once a year she makes the day-long trip to the grave of their dead son, Silas. “When she’s finished,&amp;#8221; the author tells us, as flatly as he tells us everything else, “she gets back into her car and goes home.&amp;#8221; Her Honda is twelve years old and smells of a dog the family once owned. Elisa uses an old, familiar crack in the car’s windscreen - it runs “from the lower left hand corner to to spot at eye level on the passenger side&amp;#8221; - to orient herself on the road. It’s a habit. She seems a little frame-dependant. All of this is acceptable, if drab, until the crack disappears, reality swerves, and the Honda turns abruptly into a Dodge Intrepid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elisa now finds herself in the body of a woman with the same name, whose history is as similar to her own as it is different. In this new life, she has gained several pounds. She chews gum. Her bra is uncomfortable. Her son is less dead than a computer game designer and successful internet bully. Her marriage to Derek has come apart and they’re in counselling. Everything is familiar but not the same. Thereafter, Lennon handles themes of alienation and anomie, using Elisa’s combination of slow panic and intelligent exploration of her new existence to show us that her fit with the life she’s lost is no better than her fit with the one she’s gained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who - if anyone - is undergoing the fugue, the psychotic break, here? The original Elisa, who feels she has jumped lives? Or the “new&amp;#8221; Elisa, who suddenly believes she is an interloper in her own life? The constant interrogation of identity, the sense of being at a loss about yourself not simply because you have changed but because the change forces you to question your entire context, gives &lt;em&gt;Familiar&lt;/em&gt; a faintly Hitchcockian resonance, to go with its outright reification of the &lt;em&gt;Talking Heads&lt;/em&gt; song “Road to Nowhere&amp;#8221; and its sly nod to David Lynch’s &lt;em&gt;Lost Highway&lt;/em&gt;. It also has some of Hitchcock’s mischievous humour: Lennon damps down the weirder elements of the story - its implications of quantum indeteminacy and many-worlds theory - by having Elisa navigate a crank culture of conventions and messageboards as she searches for someone who can give her an understanding of the physics of her situation. If, of course, there are any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a very readable novel but the part I found most readable was the beginning, that strangely matter-of-fact and melancholy narration of Elisa’s original life. These sad, stiflingly quotidian events pulled me through thirteen or fourteen pages without a thought - except to wonder why I was so immersed by the ordinary. I couldn’t, in the end, see why the book needed a quantum shift or Lucretian &lt;em&gt;clinamen&lt;/em&gt; to illuminate its subject. One world, one set of ordinary human emotional dislocations, would have been enough. The moment the crack in the windscreen ceased to be a metaphor and became the conduit of an actual transition, &lt;em&gt;Familiar&lt;/em&gt; became a less interesting solution to its own problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.arcfinity.org/buy.php#previous-issues"&gt;Read M John Harrison&amp;#8217;s story &amp;#8220;In Autotelia&amp;#8221; in Arc 1.1&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60920359296</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60920359296</guid><pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 10:00:39 +0100</pubDate><category>book</category><category>review</category><category>alternate world</category><category>doppelganger</category></item><item><title>We're watching FORCED ENTERTAINMENT do the future</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Sheffield&amp;#8217;s notorious theatrical troublemakers have watched one too many TED talks, and this is the predictably scabrous result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/MW7IHoBgBYc" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tomorrow&amp;#8217;s Parties&lt;/em&gt; - a series of &amp;#8220;utopian and dystopian visions, science fiction scenarios, political nightmares and absurd fantasies&amp;#8221; - infests the Crucible Studio, Sheffield on 3 and 4 October 2013 at 7.45pm. If you can make it, drop us a line on Twitter and we&amp;#8217;ll give you a guest spot on the blog to tell us about it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60848121479</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60848121479</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 16:31:58 +0100</pubDate><category>theatre</category><category>satire</category><category>premiere</category><category>uk premiere</category><category>monologue</category><category>futurology</category><category>predictions</category><category>pundits</category></item><item><title>We’re reading MR. PENUMBRA’S 24-HOUR BOOKSTORE By Robin Sloan</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.taraisabellaburton.com/"&gt;Tara Isabella Burton&lt;/a&gt; discovers that ancient conspiracies are no match for modern search engines.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://media.tumblr.com/5b3ffe4b49235f363af097ce15ab530f/tumblr_inline_msvmna3Hvo1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;small&gt;Atlantic, PPB £12.99 / Farrar, Straus and Giroux, PPB $9.00&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A casual bookshelf browser encountering &lt;em&gt;Mr. Penumbra&amp;#8217;s 24-Hour Bookstore&lt;/em&gt;, Robin Sloan&amp;#8217;s tantalizingly-titled debut novel, might be forgiven for expecting an aesthetic as Gothic, musty and gleefully old-fashioned as the dead-tree trade itself. The first paragraph of the novel ticks all the necessary bibliophiliac boxes - bookshop ladders so tall we cannot see the ground beneath our feet; the shadows of bats flitting over the covers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately - or unfortunately - Sloan swiftly reminds us that we are in the present day, and so cracked spines and dog-eared pages must give way to laptops, browser tabs, e-books, Google, Apple, and Twitter (to reference only those technological touchstones that get a mention in the book&amp;#8217;s first three pages). Clay Jannon, the book&amp;#8217;s affable if vaguely sketched protagonist, is a graphic designer, coder, and occasional social media impresario newly unemployed in the wake of the recession. Desperate for a source of income, he answers a Craigslist ad and takes a job at Mr. Penumbra&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;24-hour bookstore&amp;#8221;, a labyrinth of shelves and ladders, obscure volumes, and inscrutable categorisation: exactly the kind of place, in other words, that Clay&amp;#8217;s Kindle-toting contemporaries have put out of business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way an independent bookstore can stay open in San Francisco, Clay soon discovers, is to be inextricably linked to a centuries-old conspiracy. As Clay delves deeper into the world of Mr. Penumbra&amp;#8217;s mysterious bookshop - and its no less enigmatic customers - he finds himself drawn into the world of dead-tree-books and their equally desiccated owners, even as he uses all the technological tools at his disposal (and, via a conveniently employed love interest, the resources of Google) to uncover the bookstore&amp;#8217;s secrets and those of the Unbroken Spine, the Illuminati-esque global society of bibliophiles whose quest for the usual MacGuffins (breaking an ancient code, gaining eternal life) keeps the bookstore alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conceit underpinning &lt;em&gt;Mr. Penumbra&amp;#8217;s 24-Hour Bookstore - The Da Vinci Code&lt;/em&gt; investigated with the computing power of the twenty-first-century - is a clever one. The narrative is compelling and highly readable, the prose deft and unobtrusive. The plot speeds along without too much meandering, in a straightforward manner recalling the &lt;em&gt;Dungeons and Dragons&lt;/em&gt; adventures Clay and Neel recall fondly from their childhoods. Such problems as arise are solved briskly and expediently, more often than not with the aid of the internet But for such an ostensible love letter to the written word, in all its myriad forms, &lt;em&gt;Mr. Penumbra&amp;#8217;s 24-Hour Bookstore&lt;/em&gt; often feels surprisingly perfunctory. Clay&amp;#8217;s relationship with his girlfriend Kat, whose only defining characteristics seem to be that she&amp;#8217;s pretty and works for Google, comes across less a genuine human connection than a device generated by a plot algorithm. So too Neel, Clay&amp;#8217;s best friend (like Kat, a convenient character to have on hand – his wealth allows Sloan to wave aside any financially troublesome elements of the plot). Neel’s function in the story never goes beyond the merely pragmatic. Even Penumbra himself, all wizened brows and trembling lips, remains more a type than a fully fleshed-out character, diminishing the emotional heft of their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"A man walking fast down a dark lonely street. Quick steps and hard breathing, all wonder and need." Thus does Clay Jannon implore his readers, in a rare moment of quiet lyricism, to remember the book he plans to write – his account of the secrets of Mr. Penumbra and his mysterious bookshop. But such promise comes too little, too late. Would that this were the book he had written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/T_I_Burton"&gt;@T_I_Burton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also on the blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60451610006/were-reading-the-bone-season-by-samantha-shannon"&gt;Samantha Shannon’s The Bone Season&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/51137857082/weve-been-to-bristol-to-see-pages-fall-like-ash"&gt;Tim Maughan explores a book made of Bristol.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60831225498</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60831225498</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 10:00:56 +0100</pubDate><category>book</category><category>review</category><category>bookshop</category><category>conspiracy</category><category>literary thriller</category></item><item><title>We watched LEAVING PLANET EARTH at the Edinburgh International Festival</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.paulreviewsbooks.co.uk"&gt;Paul F. Cockburn&lt;/a&gt; joined a theatre audience literally transported to another place.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img src="http://media.tumblr.com/093b34b304c3c41a42e454b48d870cff/tumblr_inline_mspxh1vQvh1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Edinburgh International Festival remains the “official&amp;#8221; Edinburgh Festival, the Establishment against which everything else happening in the Scottish capital during August (and beyond) somehow kicks. Including, most obviously, the behemoth that is the Edinburgh Festival Fringe, which has long since overshadowed the EIF in scale. Co-ordinated, themed and commissioned years in advance, EIF retains a sense of being about “proper&amp;#8221; (ie classical) music, opera and theatre. It’s surely a sign of the times that 2013 saw the EIF curate what was undoubtedly a work of science fiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In part, this was an offshoot of one of the 2012 EIF’s main themes: technology. &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.eif.co.uk/leavingplanetearth"&gt;Leaving Planet Earth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is the extrapolation of our technological ability to move beyond our home world; and to play with the all the social, political and informatic consequences of a human mass-migration to the stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devised by Catrin Evans and Lewis Hetherington in conjunction with &lt;a href="http://www.gridiron.org.uk/"&gt;Scottish theatre company Grid Iron&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Leaving Planet Earth&lt;/em&gt; was a piece of site-specific theatre whose action took place a coach-ride away at the Edinburgh International Climbing Centre (EICC), some ten miles to the west of the capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audience were cast as the supposed final group of humans making the “jump&amp;#8221; to New Earth; and the drama, played out on the coach and within various parts of the EICC, unfolded as fragments of a “personal acclimatisation programme&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://media.tumblr.com/37a90be90a5e2978187588d50849c82d/tumblr_inline_mspxhgMfCE1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everything is going to plan with this colonisation. From the start, there is a great emphasis on “the Pull&amp;#8221;, a psychological condition like extreme home-sickness which eventually leaves those affected little more than lifeless husks. For “the good of the community&amp;#8221;, and indeed humanity’s future expansion into the stars, everyone submits to constant psychological screening to keep the Pull at bay, on the understanding that those who succumb will be humanely killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the inspirational leader of the colonisation of New Earth, Vela, knows that something more is needed; that, to deal with the Pull once and for all, New Earth must cut its ties with the Old. Only a few know what this will actually involve: the deliberate destruction of old planet and the many thousands who chose to remain there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chillingly, for some of the characters, this isn’t their most important concern. Vela herself is beginning to show signs of the Pull, spending more time than her colleagues think wise in the facility’s Old Earth Museum. If she succumbs, what will it mean for the future of humanity as a whole?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://media.tumblr.com/d94423a4a00ded52482fdcac7d019b0d/tumblr_inline_mspxhyomWL1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was much to enjoy in this production, not least the challenge of working out the alternative twentieth-century timeline in which a Third World War wiped out large parts of the population, yet also enabled the development of “Jump&amp;#8221; technology in the 1970s and the discovery of New Earth in 2005. But it was sometimes difficult to latch on to the human story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EIFF is an effective setting: it’s not every day you find yourself in an old roofed-over quarry. Its confusing mixture of inside and outside was exploited and explored by Paul Claydon’s lighting and Philip Pinsky’s soundscapes. And when the climax arrived - the symbolic cutting of all ties with Old Earth - we did feel a real sense of abandonment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/paulfcockburn"&gt;@paulfcockburn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also on the blog: &lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/54989167963/were-exploring-hari-kunzrus-memory-palace-at-londons"&gt;Nick Harkaway explores Hari Kunzru’s Memory Palace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60739925395</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60739925395</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2013 10:00:32 +0100</pubDate><category>theatre</category><category>review</category><category>colonisation</category><category>space travel</category><category>edinburgh</category></item><item><title>THIS WEEK: 6 September 2013</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This week, &lt;em&gt;Arc&lt;/em&gt; accepted &lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/58639538540/were-improving-reality-with-honor-harger"&gt;an invitation to Brighton&lt;/a&gt; in an effort to improve reality:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/59716533544/tobias-revell-confronts-bitter-reality"&gt;Tobias Revell&lt;/a&gt; reckons world-building is a political act&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60062112327/georgina-voss-performs-a-literary-heimlich-manoeuvre"&gt;Georgina Voss&lt;/a&gt; contemplates the future of food - and finds herself channeling Charlton Heston&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60164228912/paul-graham-raven-someone-elses-problem"&gt;Paul Graham Raven&lt;/a&gt; returns to the sewer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Also this week:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60451610006/were-reading-the-bone-season-by-samantha-shannon"&gt;Tara Isabella Burton&lt;/a&gt; predicts a promising if uncertain future for Samantha Shannon&amp;#8217;s epic &lt;em&gt;Bone Season&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and, from his eyrie on Elysium, &lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/59298123978/were-watching-elysium-by-neill-blomkamp"&gt;Sumit Paul-Choudhury &lt;/a&gt;concludes that Hollywood is better off not trying to predict the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60453134867</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60453134867</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 16:06:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><title>We’re reading THE BONE SEASON by Samantha Shannon</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.taraisabellaburton.com"&gt;Tara Isabella Burton&lt;/a&gt; explores a built-up area.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/5be77aa542ed8bdaeb0f9e2b770aa408/tumblr_inline_mspkl7n5891qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;small&gt;Bloomsbury, HB £12.99&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is difficult not to feel a degree of sympathy for Samantha Shannon, whose debut novel, the sprawling, series-booting &lt;em&gt;The Bone Season&lt;/em&gt; came out from Bloomsbury on August 20. Bloomsbury&amp;#8217;s PR people have been heralding her arrival on the fantasy-dystopia scene with an uncomfortable blend of hyberbole, hagiography, and hubris: a seven-book deal, complete with film optioning courtesy of &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; actor Andy Serkis and &lt;em&gt;Bridget Jones&amp;#8217;s Diary&lt;/em&gt;'s Jonathan Cavendish, eighteen foreign-language sales, a breathlessly-updated blog, fan art. Bloomsbury's press release features plenty of adjectives like “staggering” (the young age of the author) and “dizzying” (her imagination) while saying comparatively little about the book itself. The problem is – there is nowhere to go but down. At best, &lt;em&gt;The Bone Season&lt;/em&gt; only confirms Bloomsbury&amp;#8217;s soaring expectations; at worst, Shannon is prematurely consigned to the purgatorial obscurity of one-hit-wonders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is: it could be a lot worse. Blending the Dickensian and the futuristic, Shannon&amp;#8217;s dystopian Scion, an alternate-history London, is a delight of a concept. (Nutshell backstory: Edward the VII may or may not have been Jack the Ripper and/or had psychic powers: chaos ensues) Here, Cockney-accented petty criminals engage in illegal clairvoyant activity under the service of powerful “mime lords”; the terrifying urban sprawl of Dickens&amp;#8217; imagination is a prime candidate for reinvention as the archetypical dystopian metropolis (the novel&amp;#8217;s best character, sadly underutilised, is essentially Fagin with magic.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That this world is introduced to us by means of tortured exposition and plenty of world-specific jargon (there&amp;#8217;s a glossary in the back) is somewhat forgiveable: Shannon&amp;#8217;s vision is sweeping enough to buy her a degree of readerly goodwill. But the novel never quite convinces as a fully-realised world. The facts come in plentiful and fast, supplemented by page after page of explanatory map and diagram, but the story holding them together often feels devoid of real atmosphere, reading in its driest passages like a four hundred-fifty-page book proposal rather than a novel proper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of this is down to the voice of the narrator, Paige, a nineteen-year-old clairvoyant-criminal turned unwitting heroine. She sounds like a perfectly normal teenage girl in twenty-first century London: a wasted opportunity to create mood through character. While we&amp;#8217;re told that Paige, like a suspiciously high number of teenage protagonists in fantasy novels, possesses special potential far beyond that of other clairvoyants, we get little sense of what makes her special &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;; she is likeable enough, with little trace of the irritating solipsism or soppy romanticism that have afflicted recent notable YA heroines, but she’s hardly distinctive or well drawn. (That much of her most emotionally revealing backstory is given in late-stage flashbacks hardly helps.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This difficulty is exacerbated by the fact that we leave behind the most interesting elements of the story within the first hundred pages, after which Paige is kidnapped and taken to a hidden alt-Oxford, a penal colony-slash-detention centre for clairvoyants controlled by the enigmatic race of Rephaites, who have struck a devil&amp;#8217;s bargain with the Scion government as a means of fending off a common enemy (the Emim, mysterious and anodyne). This alternate Oxford is, despite plenty of exposition, rendered more sketchily than Scion – surprising, given the pre-eminence of the musty Oxonian aesthetic in fantasy from &lt;em&gt;Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt; to Philip Pullman. (At least Paige&amp;#8217;s taciturn Rephaite “keeper”, Warden, emerges as an intriguing source of Brontean broodery.) The introduction of a second new atmosphere, with its own myths and rules, soon becomes overwhelming in a novel already over-stuffed with the fruits of “world-building”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Shannon&amp;#8217;s prose is extremely readable, even if the pacing verges on the sluggish (here, too, it&amp;#8217;s possible to wonder if external forces are to blame – the book is the first of a planned seven, although the story as told seems better suited for a trilogy), and her vision of Scion, mime-lords and all, remains ripe with epic possibility. The ending of &lt;em&gt;The Bone Season&lt;/em&gt; hints at more Scion-centric sequels, and with it, the possibility of Shannon hitting her authorial stride. If future books deliver more concretely on the potent promise of the concept, Scion may prove well worth revisiting.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60451610006</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60451610006</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 15:38:00 +0100</pubDate><category>review</category><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>young adult</category><category>london</category></item><item><title>PAUL GRAHAM RAVEN: someone else's problem?</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Thursday September 5, foresight consultant and critic Paul Graham Raven talked to &lt;a href="http://www.lighthouse.org.uk/programme/improving-reality-2013"&gt;Improving Reality&lt;/a&gt; about why infrastructure - arguably the greatest of all human achievements - fills so many of us with a kind of dread.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We asked him where the trouble began.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/a7a6201939d6a2f0eb0ff6c2707b13e4/tumblr_inline_mscu7bGPH71qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big challenges in discussing infrastructure is defining what infrastructure is - and I&amp;#8217;ve found that one good way to do that is to jolt you out of that frame of reference in which&amp;#8221;infrastructure&amp;#8221; refers to a baffling panoply of complicated things from container ships to wind-farms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s do some time travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, I&amp;#8217;m going to borrow from Donna Haraway and claim that human beings have always been cyborgs. &lt;a href="http://www.egs.edu/faculty/donna-haraway/articles/donna-haraway-a-cyborg-manifesto/"&gt;All four of Haraway&amp;#8217;s definitions of the cyborg are of interest&lt;/a&gt;, but the important one here is: &lt;em&gt;the cyborg as a hybrid system comprising both living and inanimate material&lt;/em&gt;. As soon as our hunter-gatherer forebears learned how to knap flints and sling their babies across their backs in animal skins, they were cyborgs: organic creatures extending their baseline abilities by the use of prostheses, the use of &lt;em&gt;tools&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Yes, many primates and other animals use tools, but they&amp;#8217;re part-timers; tools extend them, but don&amp;#8217;t &lt;em&gt;define&lt;/em&gt; them.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hunter-gatherer culture was nomadic, clannish, matrilinear and possibly polyandrous. I don&amp;#8217;t buy the old saw about their &amp;#8220;complete harmony with the landscape&amp;#8221; or whatever. Human activity shaped the environment pretty early on, by over-hunting game to extinction, and by deploying fire. Still, having to follow their food supplies limited the time people could spend meddling with the world to make it more convenient for them. Instead, they meddled with themselves. Their only tools were what they could carry, or make to order at point of use: flint blades, wooden spears, bone needles, crude clothes of skin. These were what I call &lt;em&gt;pure&lt;/em&gt; tools: tools that do what they do in and of themselves, independent of anything else; tools you can take and use anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hunter-gatherers were collectives of cyborgs: working as groups, but possessing individual augmentations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hunter-gathering gave way gradually to agriculture, and it&amp;#8217;s at this point that the first crude infrastructures appear. A sedentary lifestyle increased the number and diversity of pure tools you could have, because you no longer needed to carry them all. It also changed the opportunity cost of engineering your environment: if you know you&amp;#8217;re going to be in the same spot for years to come, clearing a wide path or digging irrigation ditches stops being a waste of time and calories and becomes a long-term investment enabling easier access to food sources and water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infrastructures are a sort of tool: they&amp;#8217;re a prosthesis, an extension of baseline human abilities. But they aren&amp;#8217;t pure tools, because they&amp;#8217;re inherently embedded in the landscape, and hence they’re not portable (even if the concept is). Or we could think of infrastructures as metatools, enabling the development and deployment of more complex (less pure) tools, and magnifying their effects and utility. An irrigation ditch, for example, changes the parameters of subsistence farming: it saves you time and effort (no more trekking to the river and back), which you can spend on tending your crops, deterring pests, working out ways to plant faster, harvest better yields, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a downside, of course. Infrastructure - not agriculture itself, but the environmental alterations which made agriculture more viable - tied &lt;em&gt;Homo sap&lt;/em&gt; communities to specific locations. You stay for the convenience, and after a while your population expands and you get accustomed to that convenience. You stop practicing the old ways of surviving without it. You&amp;#8217;re hooked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;#8217;s not just you that&amp;#8217;s dependent on infrastructure, the way an earlier you was dependent on being able to knap flint and whittle bone. No - you&amp;#8217;re dependent on infrastructure &lt;em&gt;as a community&lt;/em&gt;. The prostheses upon which your life now depends are augmentations not of your own body, but of the collective body of your tribe or village.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations: you&amp;#8217;ve just transitioned from being a collective of cyborgs to being a cyborg collective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(We&amp;#8217;ve been one ever since.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is of interest, I think, that this is also the historical point at which we believe patriarchal social structures emerged, based around the control of access to land and resources. Also, the emergence of specialisation: infrastructure freed you up from huntin&amp;#8217; and gatherin&amp;#8217; so you could learn to throw pots, make clothes, trade stuff, and so on. Takeaway point: by freeing us from toil, infrastructure trapped us in new toils, and the culture of unavoidable dependency means you can&amp;#8217;t just walk away and start again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure is your life support system, your Hostile Environment Suit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, you could perhaps survive without it, but you wouldn&amp;#8217;t recognise the experience as &lt;em&gt;living&lt;/em&gt;. This is why I wish Randian libertarians would just piss off and &amp;#8220;go Galt&amp;#8221; like they always threaten to; it&amp;#8217;d cure them of their venal philosophy pretty fucking fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also exposes the Hairshirt Green delusion. Maybe those folk really would enjoy a return to perpetual nomadic graft, but they fail to realise that it&amp;#8217;s only due to the continued development and enhancement of infrastructure that the planet can support more than a few hundred million people. So sure, maybe &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can go back to living light upon the land - but first, you have to pick which other 6.9 billion human beings have to die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure&amp;#8217;s a trap we sprung on ourselves long, long ago. And while it&amp;#8217;s important to note that fact, there&amp;#8217;s no point in lamenting it, because &lt;em&gt;we can&amp;#8217;t go back&lt;/em&gt; - not without literal gigadeaths. The collective body cannot survive without infrastructure, and (with a few notable exceptions, fewer every year) the individual cannot survive in the interstices where infrastructure does not reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure is the technological metasystem which extracts, processes and distributes the resources that keep us alive. It is also the technological metasystem that has altered our biosphere to an unprecedented degree, to the point where - ironically enough - it may render it unable to support civilisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s broken, but we literally can&amp;#8217;t live without it. There&amp;#8217;s no going back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our only option is to fix it. The way out is through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@PaulGrahamRaven&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60164228912</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60164228912</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2013 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate><category>history</category><category>prehistory</category><category>agriculture</category><category>farming</category><category>Lighthouse</category><category>Brighton</category><category>ireality</category><category>conference</category></item><item><title>GEORGINA VOSS performs a literary Heimlich manoeuvre</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Voss, a researcher and writer investigating design, gender and ethics, is currently working on a book entitled &lt;/em&gt;Stigma and the Shaping of the Pornography Industry.&lt;em&gt; On Thursday 5 September she spoke at &lt;a href="http://www.lighthouse.org.uk/programme/improving-reality-2013"&gt;Improving Reality&lt;/a&gt; about the power-plays underlying the futurology business. We asked her what agitates her about the way we talk about the future. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/1a74cd8fba3125c1a5a8bbf6579c4c8c/tumblr_inline_mscrw7bspu1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"Write for the Arc blog", they said; "talk about something that sticks in your craw". And what sticks in the craw more than Jamie Oliver flobbering on about poor people’s food choices? At next week’s Improving Reality conference I’ll be talking about the social and economic forces which drive and skew notions of reality, touching on expensive chicken and cheap (as) chips. In Oliver’s world, poor people’s food choices are shaped by individual laziness and lack of education, not a great big crunchy socio-economic power dynamic that reduces "choice" down to the thinnest wafer of possibility (yes, Oliver, thinner even than a slice of pukka pineapple).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s talk about food. Let’s talk about who dreams up food for future populations. Let’s talk about a future where food itself has been done away with and we’re chugging down vats of &amp;#8220;powdered starch, whey protein, olive oil and raw chemical powders&amp;#8221; - meal substitutes which supply all of a human body’s daily nutritional needs. Meet Soylent (really), engineer Rob Rhinehart’s attempt to replace food entirely with a gloopy, gunky meal-substitute drink. Picked up by various tech blogs, not least because of its name, Soylent is, &lt;a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/05/03/silicon-valley-tries-to-reinvent-food-literally/"&gt;TechCrunch tells us&lt;/a&gt;, likely to land a decent round of venture capital funding. It’s also a pretty good example of why notions of improving reality aren’t straightforward propositions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soylent, although apparently &amp;#8220;delicious&amp;#8221;, is textureless gunk designed to be downed and then forgotten. Food, too, is delicious, in many more ways than Soylent can aspire to. Food is also personal and political. It carries enormous social meaning: a demonstration of love, of forgiveness, of seduction. One of my favourite short stories is &amp;#8220;A Lesbian Appetite&amp;#8221; by Dorothy Allison, in which the protagonist recounts her previous relationships through the food she ate with her girlfriends. Appetites do not exists in a vacuum. I am particularly fond of Allison’s descriptions of Lee, the self-righteous bossy health-food nut, who gets thrown over for Marty, an Atlanta girl who provides chocolate milkshakes and promises of barbeque. Food is also tied up with class politics, race politics, gender politics, and various intersections thereof. We (I) may be capable of pie-ing through a box of Jaffa Cakes in under five minutes, but food leaves its imprint on the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science fiction writers know this, and the way that food gets presented in their unreal worlds says much about our own realities. &lt;a href="http://www.academia.edu/3132030/Better_Made_Up_The_Mutual_Influence_of_Science_Fiction_and_Innovation"&gt;As my co-authors and I have discussed elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, the original &lt;em&gt;Soylent Green&lt;/em&gt; was a comment on the fears and aversions associated with mass-produced algae as a remedy for global hunger. Post-World War Two, recommendations were made to move towards non-traditional agricultural methods, including the large scale farming of algae as a foodstuff. Early NASA research into the use of algae in long spaceflights concluded that the green stuff was suitable as a nutritional supplement but not much else. In &lt;em&gt;Soylent Green&lt;/em&gt; (adapted from Harry Harrison’s 1966 novel &lt;em&gt;Make Room! Make Room!&lt;/em&gt;) the eponymous food is a wafer, issued as a ration and allegedly made of algae to meet the nutritional needs of an overpopulated world. At the film’s climax, the wafer is shown not to be made of plankton, as the ocean’s resources are depleted; it’s made of human corpses instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soylent Green&lt;/em&gt; (1973) explores the political dimensions of food substitution, industrialised food production and rapidly growing populations in a way that the coverage of Soylent (2013) has not. Soylent’s invention was borne of Rhinehart’s desire not to have to clean his dishes after he had eaten, and this desire - of a young, employed male in California who finds no pleasure in the purchase, preparation or consumption of food - is not necessarily the desire (or need) of other populations. Abstracting the culture of food into the nutritional qualities of fuel is not just an efficiency process; it imposes a version of reality where eating is no longer a satisfying, social, even sensual activity to be shared with friends and loved ones. Food has become a necessary evil which gets in the way of more important things. Even the &amp;#8220;benefits&amp;#8221; of Soylent contain certain value judgements: providing it as a cheap nutrition fix for the poor does little to address all the other systemic problems: &lt;a href="http://fooddeserts.org/"&gt;food deserts&lt;/a&gt;, healthcare provision, subsidised industrial corn production&amp;#8230; It’s no coincidence that in sci-fi dystopias, mass-produced nutri-gunk is the domain of the poor whilst the rich get steak. And please God, no-one tell Jamie Oliver about Soylent: the last thing anyone needs is a banging recipe for powdered starch slop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@gsvoss&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60062112327</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/60062112327</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2013 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate><category>nutrition</category><category>futurology</category><category>science fiction</category><category>fast food</category><category>Brighton</category><category>Lighthouse</category><category>ireality</category></item><item><title>TOBIAS REVELL confronts bitter reality </title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At Thursday’s &lt;a href="http://www.lighthouse.org.uk/programme/improving-reality-2013"&gt;Improving Reality conference&lt;/a&gt;, Revell – an artist, designer, and an associate at Superflux - explored the future of infrastructure. Armed with new materials and techniques, we may be able to grow our way out of our current problems. The thing is, do we dare?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/d87ea649b114cd9357cf990dd8142420/tumblr_inline_msbdk5BBJh1qz4rgp.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans can build worlds. So far as we know, we are unique amongst our fellow animals in that simulative ability; to animate a fiction in our mind and place within it the matrix of anxieties, fears, hopes and aspirations that we each have. We take a god’s-eye-view of this imaginary space and annotate the lives of the people and artefacts we have put in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children are the best, most promiscuous and most fastidious world-builders. They construct startlingly complex micro-universes to play out fictional interactions and stories that, inadvertently, grow in them an empathy with the world. Play and fantasy become the weapons children use to fight the fog of solipsism they are born with from distorting and blurring reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it’s time we re-armed ourselves. Between the catastrophe of the past we’ve wrought and the so obvious and raw, almost-unspeakable terror of the centuries to come, we’re rediscovering that we are still children, humbled and gazing in wonder at the scale of our futures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now the fog is starting to come into focus: that obfuscating haze of progress and technology, of gadgets and celebrity that so seamlessly blurs the background and hides the dizzying depths of reality. The world-builders we left in charge of our future figured that we didn’t need to know the details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now we live on someone else’s world: the world of the Stacks, the NSA, the Troika, the Smart City, the Cloud, Big Pharma, Big Ag, Big Scoop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slowly our complicity in this construction is becoming clear. We realise that the only way to get what we wanted out of our brave new capitalist paradise was to give our consent to living in a fiction - a fiction thinly-layered on a world of incredible depth and complexity that we let the fog creep into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans can build worlds and I think it’s time we re-armed ourselves. At some point we decided that this was a childish thing, or that no-one has the right to build worlds, or that it meant nothing. And while we were staring at the fog, the weapon we thought a toy was used against us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@tobias_revell&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/59716533544</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/59716533544</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 23:36:00 +0100</pubDate><category>design</category><category>infrastructure</category><category>capitalism</category><category>futurology</category><category>Lighthouse</category><category>ireality</category><category>Brighton</category><category>conference</category></item><item><title>We're watching ELYSIUM by Neill Blomkamp </title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maybe Hollywood&amp;#8217;s better off getting the future wrong, says &lt;a href="http://sumit.paul-choudhury.com"&gt;Sumit Paul-Choudhury&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/ea3f23f396c27d873f048743bb425800/tumblr_inline_ms383eGKDC1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spoilers below.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Why can&amp;#8217;t sci-fi films get to grips with what the future might actually be like?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;So &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/film/2013/aug/22/why-hollywood-future-wrong-elysium"&gt;asks Joe Queenan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;"More than a century into the future, the characters talk like people from the early 21st century, dress like people from the early 21st century, sport tattoos like people from the early 21st century, and wear cobalt trouser suits like people from … 1987," he writes of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elysium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span&gt;, the long-awaited second film from &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1136608/"&gt;District 9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span&gt; creator &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0088955/"&gt;Neill Blomkamp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;"And, oh yes, in 2154, unemployed thugs will still be walking around in vests. I don&amp;#8217;t get it. I just don&amp;#8217;t. Does anyone seriously believe that, 141 years from now, people will still try to scare anyone by wearing tattoos?" &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;There is, of course, a ready line of argument against such criticisms, namely that science fiction movies - at least &amp;#8220;intelligent&amp;#8221; ones such as &lt;em&gt;Elysium&lt;/em&gt; - are intended to allegorise the present, not illustrate the future. And that allegory is only resonant with a mass audience when dressed up in familiar signifiers: thug tattoos for scofflaws, sharp suits for one-percenters. Futuristic, not futurological.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;So let&amp;#8217;s set aside &lt;em&gt;Elysium&lt;/em&gt;'s alleged failure to portray a plausible vision of the future - at least for the moment. Matt Damon's Max, an ex-jailbird trying to keep his nose clean in the slums of Los Angeles, has just days to live after an accident at the factory where (irony alert!) he assembles the droids that now keep the Earth's downtrodden population in line. An exoskeletal graft transforms him into a &amp;#8220;favela ninja&amp;#8221; determined to infiltrate Elysium, an orbiting space station lined with McMansions where the champagne flows freely - and more pertinently for Max, so does the medical care.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/374abcb06d3a198d3a77eb7a4fad8db0/tumblr_inline_ms3856YfMg1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;So far, so good. Plenty of allegorical plates are set spinning in the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;first act&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: homeland security, boat people, total surveillance, universal healthcare. Alas, they all come crashing down as the film dissolves into little more than a long - not to say interminable - chase sequence.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;When Max does eventually reach Elysium, his time is spent battling his way through a variety of vacant medical and industrial facilities: we get a well-worn physical clash, rather than an intriguing culture clash, with Elysium&amp;#8217;s occupants. Most disappointingly, his nemesis ultimately turns out not to be Jodie Foster&amp;#8217;s icy security director Delacourt, who is as implacably determined to protect Elysium as Max is to penetrate it; but the bestial rōnin Kruger, played with scenery-chewing gusto by Sharlto Copley.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potential for a thoughtful, mutivalent encounter between between heaven and earth evaporates, a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Rg-u6-pgdwo"&gt;cyborg slugfest&lt;/a&gt; taking its place. And the ending, in which Elysium&amp;#8217;s bleeding-edge healthcare system is transformed at the click of a button into SpaceObamaCare, without so much as a nod to resource or population constraints, rings hollow. (Parallel criticisms could also be made of &lt;em&gt;District 9&lt;/em&gt;; but what&amp;#8217;s excusable and even exhilarating in a scrappy underdog debut is less enticing in a megabucks sophomore effort.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;So &lt;em&gt;Elysium&lt;/em&gt; not only fails as prediction but also, in large part, as allegory, for all that it may succeed as a box-office friendly summer blockbuster. But perversely, its failure of futurology - or more accurately, its indifference to it - is one of its strengths. Queenan may decry its contemporary and palaeofuturistic motifs, but they give it visual and symbolic heft: w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;hile the film&amp;#8217;s narrative doesn&amp;#8217;t &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;satisfactorily&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; explore &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;the intersection of its utopian and dystopian futures, its design does - and it does so precisely through carefully cultivated atemporality. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Elysium&amp;#8217;s spoked &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanford_torus"&gt;Stanford torus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; is taken directly from Seventies &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://space.mike-combs.com/gallery.htm"&gt;concept illustrations of space habitats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, its groomed lawns strolled by manicured inhabitants against a horizon that rises to become the sky. But the imagery is détourned neatly by the knowledge that its inhabitants are the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://time100.time.com/"&gt;TIME 100&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, not NASA&amp;#8217;s envisaged 10,000 homesteaders. And there&amp;#8217;s the further contrast with &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;the collapsonomic milieu of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;Children of Men&lt;/em&gt; down below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there&amp;#8217;s its juxtaposition of &lt;a href="http://www.vulture.com/2013/08/syd-mead-design-blade-runner-aliens-elysium.html"&gt;Syd Mead-sleek&lt;/a&gt; personal shuttles with &lt;a href="http://www.newscientist.com/blogs/culturelab/2011/09/chris-foss-the-joy-of.html"&gt;Chris Foss-style&lt;/a&gt; gunships and tramp steamers. Max&amp;#8217;s painfully installed &lt;span&gt;cyborg tech harks back to cyberpunky offerings like &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0099740/"&gt;Richard Stanley&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;Hardware&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;; his promised salvation, on the other hand, lies within the Elysians&amp;#8217; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;pristine&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;magical medipods.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Internal_view_of_the_Stanford_torus.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/fbbea409907a64a87272a0e9cc2773c8/tumblr_inline_ms38o6WPGb1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elysium&lt;/em&gt; offers a collage of futures, then: none of them individually credible, but collectively redolent of possibiity. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Like Rian &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Johnson&amp;#8217;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;Looper&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span&gt;, it mixes and matches to make its point; fans of the future can amuse themselves filling in the interstices and charting out the intersections&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;. And l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;ike the Tom Cruise vehicle &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oblivion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span&gt;, which met with a similarly lukewarm critical response earlier this year, its context is more interesting than its content. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Maybe that&amp;#8217;s where we are with the new wave of &amp;#8220;intelligent&amp;#8221; science fiction blockbusters: what smarts they have take the form not of prediction, nor of allegory, but of palimpsest: overwriting yesterday&amp;#8217;s futures with today&amp;#8217;s preoccupations. It&amp;#8217;s hard to imagine a film that set out to be purely predictive being anything other than preachy or pedantic; drawing on our collective imaginings, in visual codes we can readily grasp, creates visions that are all the more powerful for their imperfection. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Megabucks design fiction: perhaps that&amp;#8217;s all science fiction films can ever aspire to be, after all. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Why don&amp;#8217;t sci-films get to grips with what the future might really be like? &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Perhaps because it&amp;#8217;s more interesting to get it wrong.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/59298123978</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/59298123978</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2013 15:01:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><title>We’re IMPROVING REALITY with Honor Harger</title><description>&lt;p&gt;On September 5, Reality gets Improved &lt;a href="http://lighthouse.org.uk/programme/improving-reality-2013"&gt;in a day-long conference organised by Lighthouse&lt;/a&gt;, an arts agency in South East England that supports, commissions and showcases new work by artists and filmmakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in its third year, the conference explores how artists and designers are shifting our perceptions of the world. &lt;a href="http://www.panix.com/~keller/"&gt;Keller Easterling&lt;/a&gt;, artist and synthetic biologist &lt;a href="http://www.daisyginsberg.com/"&gt;Daisy Ginsberg&lt;/a&gt;, and futurist &lt;a href="http://justinpickard.net/"&gt;Justin Pickard&lt;/a&gt; head the bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arc&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;Improving Reality&lt;/strong&gt;’s media partner and will be covering the event in real-time. The day’s already sold out, BUT we have five tickets to give away as prizes. Just email &lt;strong&gt;arc@arcfinity.org&lt;/strong&gt; with a tweet-length (140-character) response to the following question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Which bit of your day-to-day reality needs improving today, and what imaginary machine would accomplish this?"&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tickets will go to the five best replies we’ve received by the time we get into work on &lt;strong&gt;Tuesday 27 August&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next couple of weeks we’ll be running guest blogposts from some of the speakers. But to kick things off, Arc’s editor Simon Ings asked Lighthouse’s director &lt;a href="http://about.me/honor"&gt;Honor Harger&lt;/a&gt;, the New Zealand-born curator and artist, why she wanders about with her head in the Cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/3069e7c3f483d90f0c107ec25756053a/tumblr_inline_mrqymmV5R71qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo: Ivo Näpflin / &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/liftconference/"&gt;liftconferencephotos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ARC&lt;/strong&gt;     Before we talk about the conference, or Lighthouse, I want to know how you got started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HH&lt;/strong&gt;     I guess my interest in ephemeral networks and the data space of the air comes from a lifelong interest in radio. My first job was working in a radio station, Radio One in Dunedin in New Zealand. One of its strengths was programming experimental sound and experimental music. So this interconnection between sound art and radio has been there for me from the beginning, along with the realisation, which you learn when you start out, that radio is an entirely natural phenomenon: the radio waves that we harness here on earth to use for communication are effectively caused by the activity of the sun, Radio is part of physics, part of science, part of the natural world. Yet it&amp;#8217;s also inherently connected to the development of modern human civilisation. It&amp;#8217;s very hard to imagine our world now without radio technologies. They underpin everything from communication to navigation; we literally wouldn&amp;#8217;t have the civilisation that we understand today without them. And everything that we speak about now when we talk about data infrastructures and the Cloud – all of these types of metaphors and technologies – they all began in the nineteenth century with development of telegraphy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ARC&lt;/strong&gt;     The conference has a very specific angle on this, though. It’s about how media infrastructures create our reality. How did that come about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HH&lt;/strong&gt;     We conceived Improving Reality for the very first Brighton Digital Festival that Lighthouse was involved in, back in 2011. It was intended as a companion event to dConstruct, which is one of the country’s key events for discussing the future of digital design in the UK. It regularly brings to Brighton around a thousand people from around the world. What we wanted from our event was to show how artists are part of this conversation, and how they can act as catalysts and imagineers, helping us think about how science and technology affect our experience of reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The artistic practice of one of the keynote speakers that year, an artist called Julian Oliver, was pivotal. For some time he’d been dealing with augmented reality and the ethics of augmented reality, and he’d developed a project which quite playfully and quite critically claimed that, rather than augmenting reality, we should be improving upon reality. His project, The Artvertiser, used a headset to edit out the advertising from public spaces. Go into Time Square or Piccadilly and you’re confronted by the kinds of billboards used by Coke and Nike. With the headset on, these big advertisements vanish, replaced by art. It wasn&amp;#8217;t just an idea. It was a fully operational piece of kit. And through that project he developed this discourse around how we can affect and improve our environments by hacking reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ARC     &lt;/strong&gt;Of course, you could call that sort of &amp;#8220;improvement&amp;#8221; simply the secession of the privileged. Those with the headsets get the improving pictures, while the rest of us&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HH&lt;/strong&gt;     Well, that&amp;#8217;s the thing. As soon as you start bandying around terms like improvement you&amp;#8217;re immediately in political, ethical, social territory. And we&amp;#8217;re very deliberately confronting those issues. We certainly don&amp;#8217;t want to suggest that an artist&amp;#8217;s use of technology can, if you like, uncritically lead to improvements. We&amp;#8217;re really trying to dig into people&amp;#8217;s perceptions about what technology does in their daily lives and whether it &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; create improvements, or whether it creates difficulties or obstacles. So we&amp;#8217;re very active in surveying that kind of political territory and the conference, as it’s developed over three years that we&amp;#8217;ve run it, has deliberately brought in some radical political thinking as well as the more traditional sort of technology and art presentations. And that&amp;#8217;s going to be a major thread running through this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ARC&lt;/strong&gt;     So what&amp;#8217;s the theme of this year’s conference?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HH&lt;/strong&gt;     We’ll be looking at political, social and technological infrastructures: the dark matter that underlies our contemporary life. We&amp;#8217;re interested in the way that artists, designers and architects are helping make these infrastructures more visible. After all, if we can’t see these structures, then it&amp;#8217;s very difficult for us to be able to comprehend them, let alone critique them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also interested in how artists, designers and writers imagine the future of infrastructure. There’s a kind of a parallel discipline to design fiction emerging, which we can call speculative design. Objects are being made for the specific purpose of creating conversations. Now, can we apply that same type of thinking and come up with something called infrastructure fiction? I want to see if dreaming up fictional infrastructures inspires conversations around what infrastructures should be, who they should be for and how should they be used. What are the political and social issues that attend these massive and invisible systems?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ARC&lt;/strong&gt;     What inspired this approach?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HH&lt;/strong&gt;     A couple of things. First, you’ve got &lt;a href="http://www.lighthouse.org.uk/programme/timo-arnall-collaborators-immaterials"&gt;the work of the filmmaker and designer Timo Arnall&lt;/a&gt;, which we&amp;#8217;re showing at Lighthouse at the same time as the conference. Timo&amp;#8217;s work is all about making invisible systems visible. GPS, radio frequency ID: these things that pervade our everyday lives but we can&amp;#8217;t see them. Timo creates films and objects that make those technological infrastructures visible. And, secondly, one of the keynotes this year is an architect and urbanist called Keller Easterling, who&amp;#8217;s a professor of architecture at Yale in New York and has written extensively about both physical architectural infrastructures but also political and social infrastructures and how the two relate. She&amp;#8217;s got a book coiming out called Extrastatecraft which looks at the interconnection between physical space and the network. So my hope is that, between these two perspectives - one from design and visibility, the other from politics and sociology, will act as the poles for our conversations this year.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/58639538540</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/58639538540</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2013 23:10:00 +0100</pubDate><category>lighthouse</category><category>Brighton</category><category>Honor Harger</category><category>infrastructure</category><category>design</category><category>radio</category><category>augmented reality</category><category>invisibility</category><category>Improving Reality</category><category>conference</category></item><item><title>

"It is impossible to so forecast any future conditions that depend upon the evolution of society...</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://media.tumblr.com/2216686aaf150e7ff5deb06a6a13921e/tumblr_inline_mq4oex8l6b1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"It is impossible to so forecast any future conditions that depend upon the evolution of society as to be able to govern our conduct by such a forecast; it is always the unexpected that happens, for we have to recognise not only the immediate change that is to take place, but also the reaction back upon this of the whole world within which the change takes place, and no human foresight is equal to this&amp;#8230; What we have is a method and a control in application, not an ideal to work toward."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—George Mead&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/55772078880</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/55772078880</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 11:46:42 +0100</pubDate><category>futurology</category></item><item><title>THIS WEEK: 12 July 2013</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This week, &lt;em&gt;Arc&lt;/em&gt; explored a memory palace, dabbled in Black Arts, and travelled in time with a playwright and a serial killer. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Harkaway cleaves his way through the David Bowie fans in search of &lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/54989167963/were-exploring-hari-kunzrus-memory-palace-at-londons"&gt;Hari Kunzru’s Memory Palace at the V&amp;amp;A&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leigh Alexander battles the Boss of &lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/55078380754/were-reading-you-by-austin-grossman"&gt;Austin Grossman’s You&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope Whitmore yearns to revisit &lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/55249400651/were-reading-the-other-place-by-j-b-priestley"&gt;The Other Place by J B Priestley&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liz Sourbut lays flowers and placards on the graves of &lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/55260428326/were-reading-the-shining-girls-by-lauren-beukes"&gt;Lauren Beukes’s Shining Girls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/55260911763</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/55260911763</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2013 15:51:49 +0100</pubDate></item><item><title>We’re reading THE SHINING GIRLS by Lauren Beukes</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liz Sourbut asks: Who lives in a House like this?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://media.tumblr.com/465613a1b78eb552102945dbd3dacc23/tumblr_inline_mptjkrS9Zl1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href="denied:http://www.amazon.co.uk/The-Shining-Girls-Lauren-Beukes/dp/0007464568"&gt;HarperCollins, HB £12.99&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A time-travelling serial killer is hard to catch. It’s hard even to spot a consistent MO when he’s dodging around Chicago anywhen between 1929 and 1993, killing exceptional young women in random order. Kirby Mazrachi is the one who got away, although not without horrendous injuries and an appalling psychological aftermath. She’s determined to catch the man who so nearly killed her, but the police have pretty much given up on her case and she’s not getting a lot of support from anywhere. Even Dan, the ex-homicide journalist turned sports reporter for whom she is interning on the &lt;em&gt;Sun-Times&lt;/em&gt; newspaper in 1993, would much rather she dropped her interest in the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harper Curtis, out of work and drifting like so many men during the Great Depression, is running from attackers in November 1931. He murders a blind old woman for her coat and in the pocket he finds a key. The key lets him into the House (always capitalised) and in the House he finds many strange things. Perhaps strangest of all is the time-lapse view out of the windows. The House is adrift in time, and he learns that if he concentrates he can come and go to any time he pleases between 1929 and 1993. Upstairs is a room full of apparently random artefacts and girls’ names chalked on the walls in his own handwriting. The House whispers to him, and he embarks on a killing spree, drawn to young girls who shine with potential. He meets them first as children and gives each of them a small gift. Then he returns - for him, only a day or two later; for them, years - when their potential has begun to manifest, and he kills them. Brutally. In graphic detail. Often from the viewpoint of the young woman herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harper takes his time, finding perverse sexual pleasure in the act of inflicting prolonged pain and finally death. This is not a book for the squeamish, nor, to my mind, for anyone with the faintest feminist streak in their soul. It is not pleasant to read of yet another sick, angry man with a knife taking out his frustrations on women who have done nothing whatsoever to provoke him and I was waiting for some reason, some purpose, some sense to come out of it. There was none, and perhaps that’s right, but it leaves a sick feeling behind. I did not find this an uplifting book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beukes writes confidently and well. She evokes the different eras in Chicago’s history with great clarity and conviction and, although many of the shining girls of the title have only cameo appearances, she manages to make us feel as though we know each of them within a page or two – which makes it all the more horrific when Harper arrives with his knife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kirby, the young woman who survived thanks to the intervention of her dog, is strong and determined. She never gives up. She has great courage, and it’s clear that whatever else he is, Harper (or the House he serves) is a good judge of potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very well-crafted book, carefully plotted and filled with rounded, largely likeable characters, most of whom end up dead, their potential snuffed out senselessly. What was this all about? Why did any of this happen? And - hang on - aren’t these questions the author’s job?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also on the blog: Liz Sourbut catches streins of &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="denied:http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/50566439409/were-reading-the-monsters-lament-by-robert-edric"&gt;The Monster’s Lament&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; in London’s underworld.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/55260428326</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/55260428326</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2013 15:42:00 +0100</pubDate><category>serial killer</category><category>thriller</category><category>slasher</category><category>time travel</category><category>whodunnit</category><category>novel</category><category>zoo city</category></item><item><title>We’re reading THE OTHER PLACE by J.B. Priestley </title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://hopewhitmore.wordpress.com"&gt;Hope Whitmore&lt;/a&gt; loses track of time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://media.tumblr.com/5e2314be71dfa2ae44bc09e6d322160f/tumblr_inline_mpthx4SGdc1qz4rgp.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Other-Place-Stories-Same-Sort/dp/1939140390"&gt;The Other Place, and other stories of the same sort&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br/&gt; J.B. Priestley, with a new introduction by John Baxendale&lt;br/&gt; Valancourt Books, PPB £10.99&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love the plays of J.B. Priestley for the way he takes unaware characters to a new reality or a different time, exposing them to an experience that will change their perceptions. These cosmic shifts are seemingly incidental: the surreal happens with no fuss or fanfare. It skews time in the guise of too lifelike a dream. It whispers to people as they were in the past. It walks into a family dining room in the shape of an inspector. It is low-key magic, artfully blended with the familiar; in its chill, audiences question their own reality&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the stories in &lt;em&gt;The Other Place&lt;/em&gt; mix the prosaic reality of post-World War Two life with the fantastical, but here the blend is more startling, less subtle. People are living lives that are familiar - dreary, even - but then they leave a room and take a wrong turning in time. They go through a door which leads to another world. They encounter strangers. They are given glimpses of the future. They emerge from a swim in the lake to realise they have arrived in Edwardian England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is something of the fairy tale about this approach, and the characters know it. In “Night Sequence”, Betty stops short: “Vague memories of fairy tales returned to her, tales in which the over-curious, the obstinate enquirers only cut themselves off from the good magic.” This insight rarely saves them. In the title story, “The Other Place”, the protagonist is shown a door to an idyllic world, where everyone is happy and there are no barriers between people. He moves from darkness into light, but asks for too much and is expelled from paradise: he’ll waste the rest of his life trying to reclaim it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mistake here is human, sprung from impatience. In other stories Priestley is less forgiving, setting his more arrogant characters up for a fall. Seeing the world all too clearly is an effective punishment: Sir Bernard Clipter in “Guest of Honour” shouts at a “shabby-looking oldish man, probably a foreigner” after his car nearly runs the man down. You can guess the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favourite story is the final one, “Night Sequence”. It opens as a traditional ghost story: a young couple are, arguing, stranded miles from anywhere after their car breaks down. They follow a light to the nearest house they see. What they discover here holds a mirror up to what they have become. It might possibly save their relationship and make them better people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Priestley is an old-school storyteller, beckoning us in and introducing us to his characters’ lives with seamless exposition. Reading this collection reminded me of being read to as a child. “What is madness?” he asks “What is time?” “What are we?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These final two questions, “What is Time?” and “What are we?” were inextricably linked for Priestley,m who understood that where we stand in time bears great relation on who we are. Take away time or alter it slightly and we become different. In “Look After the Strange Girl”, the main character feels completely lost and ill at ease when ripped away from the security of his own time: “Was home, then, more in time than in space?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the introduction to this new edition, John Baxendale discusses P.D. Ouspensky, whose theory of eternal recurrence interested Priestley and influenced many of these stories. Is all time happening at once, and if so, what does this mean for us? I’m not sure that Priestley knew, exactly. But his combination of curiosity and decency does not date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also on the blog: &lt;a href="http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/52623460220/were-talking-to-lee-smolin-whose-new-model-of-the"&gt;watch physicist Lee Smolin explain his new model of time.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/55249400651</link><guid>http://arcfinity.tumblr.com/post/55249400651</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2013 10:56:32 +0100</pubDate><category>uncanny</category><category>ghost stories</category><category>theatre</category><category>time travel</category><category>moral tales</category></item></channel></rss>
